Guide to the Irene D. Andrews Pace Collection of Diamond Family Bookplates
Yale University Library
Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library
Irene D. Pace Collection of Diamond Family Bookplates
early to mid-20th century
BKP 14
Pace, Irene D. Andrews
0.5 linear feet (1 box)
This collection contains numerous bookplates commissioned by various members of the Diamond Family. J. Edouard “Jack” Diamond and Elizabeth Watson Diamond were avid bookplate collectors and the proprietors of Hyacinth Press, a small private press which they operated from their home in Cleveland, OH.
Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library Special Collections 180 York Street New Haven, CT 06520 Email: haasalsc@pantheon.yale.edu Phone: (203)432-1712 Fax: (203)432-0549
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Irene D. Andrews Pace, 1963.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical Overview
Born Irene Greene Dwen, Pace was an avid bookplate collector from the early 1920s until 1962. In addition to over 150,000 plates in her collection, she also maintained a reference library related to bookplates, as well as heraldry and biographical research. Pace commissioned several hundred bookplates for herself. In 1936, she published Owners of Books: The Dissipations of a Collector.
Description of the Papers
This collection contains numerous bookplates commissioned by various members of the Diamond Family. J. Edouard “Jack” Diamond and Elizabeth Watson Diamond were avid bookplate collectors and the proprietors of Hyacinth Press, a small private press which they operated from their home in Cleveland, OH. Two works published by Hyacinth Press are also part of the Yale Bookplate Collection: Bookplates by Sara Eugenia Blake, Call # Z996.B635 B535 1940 (LC); and Bookplates of Hettie Gray Baker, Call # Z996 B25 B66 1947 (LC).
Access Terms
This collection is indexed under the following access points in Orbis, the Yale University Library online catalog.
Subjects
Bookplates--Specimens; Andrews, Irene Dwen, 1892-; Diamond, J. Edouard.; Diamond, Elizabeth Watson.
Genre/Form
Bookplates.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by the artist’s last name, according to the original order and an accompanying checklist.
Collection Contents
- Bookplates
  - patron: J. [Diamond], undated; artist: Adam, Helen; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - patron: Needlework Books, undated; artist: Adam, Helen; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - patron: J. Edouard Diamond, undated; artist: Austin, John; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - patron: J. Edouard Diamond, undated; artist: Austin, John; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - patron: E. W. D. | D., undated; artist: Bewick, Thomas; 11 items (Box 1, Folder 5)
    This folder contains 2 bookplate restrikes from a Thomas Bewick woodblock, plus 9 additional unidentified prints, which were all housed together.
  - patron: Diamond, undated; artist: Bewick, Thomas; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, undated; artist: Bewick, Thomas; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - patron: Diamond, undated; artist: le Campion, Valentin; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson, undated; artist: le Campion, Valentin; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, undated; artist: le Campion, Valentin; 5 items (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - patron: J. Edouard Diamond, undated; artist: le Campion, Valentin; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - patron: J. Edouard Diamond, undated; artist: le Campion, Valentin; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, undated; artist: Elwell, J. H.; 3 items (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - patron: Jacob Edouard Diamond, undated; artist: Eastman, William; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - patron: Diamond, undated; artist: Feint, Adrian; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, undated; artist: Feint, Adrian; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - patron: Elizabeth Diamond, undated; artist: Fingesten, Michel; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - patron: Elizabeth W. Diamond, undated; artist: Fingesten, Michel; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, undated; artist: Fingesten, Peter; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - patron: E. W. D., undated; artist: Fitzpatrick; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, undated; artist: Fleissig, V.; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, undated; artist: Fleissig, V.; 3 items (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - patron: J. Edouard Diamond, undated; artist: Hodges, Ralph; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - patron: Bettina Cambon, undated; artist: Jameson, John William; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - patron: Betsie Diamond, 1930; artist: Jameson, John William (sculp.); artist: Jeavons, W. N. (del.); 2 items (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, undated; artist: Jameson, John William; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - patron: J. Edouard Diamond, undated; artist: Jameson, John William; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - patron: Sandra, undated; artist: Jameson, J. W.; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, undated; artist: Johnson, Fridolf; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - patron: Salome Collection, undated; artist: Johnson, Fridolf; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, undated; artist: Kislinger, Max; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, undated; artist: Kronbourg, Sascha; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, undated; artist: Kronbourg, Sascha; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, undated; artist: Kronbourg, Sascha; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - patron: Elizabeth Diamond, undated; artist: Kubinyi, Kalman; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - patron: J. E. Diamond, undated; artist: Kubinyi, Kalman; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - patron: J. Edouard Diamond, undated; artist: Kubinyi, Kalman; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - patron: Jack Diamond, undated; artist: Kubinyi, Kalman; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, undated; artist: Landacre, Paul; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - patron: J. Edouard Diamond, undated; artist: Macdonald, A. N.; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - patron: J. Edouard Diamond, undated; artist: Nichols, Dale; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - patron: J. Edouard Diamond, undated; artist: Nichols, Dale; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - patron: Elizabeth Diamond, undated; artist: Perrottet, G. D.; 3 items (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - patron: Elizabeth, undated; artist: Simmons, Will; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, undated; artist: Simmons, Will; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, 1939; artist: Simmons, Will; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, 1939; artist: Simmons, Will; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, undated; artist: Simmons, Will; artist: Bayros, Franz von; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 48)
    This folder includes a bookplate that is a restrike from a copperplate by Franz von Bayros. The name was changed by Will Simmons, and the bookplate was used by Diamond in her books on music.
  - patron: J. Edouard Diamond, undated; artist: Simmons, Will; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - patron: Jack and Betsy Diamond, undated; artist: Simmons, Will; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - patron: [Unidentified], undated; artist: Simmons, Will; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, 1939; artist: Smith, Leslie Victor; 4 items (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, undated; artist: Smith, Leslie Victor; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - patron: J. Edouard Diamond, 1939; artist: Smith, Leslie Victor; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, 1915; artist: Smith, Sidney L.; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - patron: Beckydee, undated; artist: Tenniel, John, Sir; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 56)
    This folder contains a bookplate that is based on an illustration by Sir John Tenniel of the tea party from Alice’s Adventures in Wonderland.
  - patron: Elizabeth, undated; artist: Vadasz, Endre; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - patron: Diamond, undated; artist: Vadasz, Endre; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - patron: Elizabeth W. Diamond, 1939; artist: Vadasz, Endre; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - patron: J. E. Diamond, undated; artist: Vadasz, Endre; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson-Diamond, undated; artist: Vannuccini, Eurico; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - patron: Betsie D, undated; artist: Warshawsky, Alex; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, undated; artist: Wright, John Buckland; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - patron: J. Edouard Diamond, undated; artist: Wright, John Buckland; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - patron: Elizabeth Watson Diamond, 1946, undated; artist: [Unidentified]; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 65)
    This folder contains two different bookplate designs for Elizabeth Watson Diamond (signed TM, undated) and Elisabeth Watson Diamond (signed gd, dated XMAS '46).
  - Ephemera, undated; 10 items (Box 1, Folder 66)